George Humphreys Tichenor III Personal Papers 5239
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
George Humphreys Tichenor III Personal Papers
1938-1961
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Tichenor, George Humphreys, III
5239
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
Clippings (information artifacts), drafts (documents), reprints.
The collection consists of part of his personal papers. The union publications he edited will be found in the ILR Library and the Cooperator in Mann Library.
2293774
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, July 29, 2013
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, February 22, 2017
Biographical / Historical
George Tichenor III was born in New Orleans, La., on December 17, 1906, to George Humphreys Tichenor, Jr., a doctor and Gertrude Belknap. He was educated at Tulane University in New Orleans. He served as a cub reporter on the Picayune and later became a free lance writer and photographer.
He was the author of two popular novels, "Gibson" and "Manhattan Prodigal." As a free lance writer he contributed travel articles to the New York Times and many other publications. Two of his photographs appeared in the Saturday Evening Post series, "Face of America." He used pen names Gilbert Tolman, Ted Gilbert son and George Thompson as well as his own.
He was interested in the cooperative movement in the United States and served as editor of the Co-operator published by the Eastern Cooperation League from 1939-1948. He also edited Co-op Highlights and was active in the cooperative housing movement in New York City. During the second World War, he was a special consultant to the O.P.A. on consumer needs.
He was an accomplished labor Journalist, editing "The Hat Worker" of the United Hat, Cap and Millinery Workers and the "Spotlight" for the United Wire, Metal and Machine Health and Welfare Fund, Local l6l4 of the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers and Local 8lO of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters.
The Hat Worker says of him "George Tichenor contributed scores of memorable feature articles to our publication on every phase of union activities, the labor-movement, social issues and topics of general reader interest. In 1951, under his editorship, The Hat Worker was awarded a Certificate of Merit by the Eastern Labor Press Conference "for excellency in form and content." In 1953, his story about organizational activities in Medfield, Mass., titled "When the Union Came To Town," received the top award of the International Labor Press Association."
Mr. Tichenor also served on the state executive, committee of the Liberal Party of New York State.
Scope and Contents
Includes routine correspondence, reprints of articles, and newspaper clippings relating to the following issues: consumer and housing cooperatives; the role of labor unions in the cooperative movement; prospective new housing cooperatives to be built in New York City; support of the cooperative movement for the Tennessee Valley Authority; the financial condition of the Cooperator, organ of the Eastern Cooperative League; the economic condition of the hat and cap industry; the problems of small, economically marginal operations in the hat industry; the use of polls for discerning trends in consumer buying habits and public opinion in local elections; the role of labor in politics; the impact of tariffs on foreign imports of hats; the Taft-Hartley Act; support for the Liberal Party in New York; the impact of inflation on the cooperative movement; the American Labor Health Association; competition in the insurance industry; the contributions of Edward A. Filene to the credit union movement; the League of Nations; the U.S. Chamber of Commerce; consumer cooperatives; significant innovations in the retail distribution field; costs of medical care; anti-Semitism; and communism.
Also contains numerous reprints, rough drafts, newspaper clippings, and routine correspondence relating to Tichenor's various journalistic efforts.
The collection consists of part of his personal papers. The union publications he edited will be found in the ILR Library and the Cooperator in Mann Library.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Anti-communist movements -- United States; Antisemitism -- United States; Consumer cooperatives -- United States; Credit Unions -- United States; Hat trade -- Economic aspects -- United States; Housing, Cooperative -- United States; Labor unions -- United States -- Political activity; Journalists.; Working class -- Medical care -- United States; Filene, Edward Albert, 1860-1937; Tichenor, George, 1906-1959.; American Labor Health Association; Chamber of Commerce of the United States of America; Eastern Cooperatives, Inc.; League of Nations; Liberal Party of New York State; Tennessee Valley Authority; United States. Labor Management Relations Act, 1947
2293774
- I Coop Conference, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- I Cooperative Housing, 1952-1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- I Cooperative Housing - Misc., 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- I Cooperative League of U.S.A., 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- I Cooperative Movement - Articles by Tichenor, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- I Cooperative Movement - Consumer Coops, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- I Cooperator, 1949-1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Hatters - Correspondence, 1951-1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Teamsters & Hoffa, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- The Hatworker - Articles and Mateirals, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Union Spotlight - editorial materials & stories, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Union Spotlight - editorial materials & stories, 1951-1959 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- The American Family Takes to the Woods, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- American Labor Health Association, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Blue Cross, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Blue Cross Articles, 1951-1958 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Blue Cross N.Y.S. Dept. of Insurance Hearings, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Bolivian Jaguars, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Brooklyn Bridge, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Cabbies, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Camping on a Stony Budget, 1951-1958 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Confidential Story (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Cooperstown, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Credit Union Bridge, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Credit Union Nat'l. Assn., 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- "The Day I Robbed the George Washington Bridge", 1958 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Face of America, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Gaspe Story (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Filene Story, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- "How New York is Fed", 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- I, Fisherman, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Interrupting the Great Conversation, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Iron Tongue, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Kalmuks, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- "Loan Shark" Story, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Nationwide Insurance, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Oasis, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Ocracoke, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Radio Show - "The People Act", 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- This we own, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- U.S. Information Agency, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- "Woman Flyers", 1952 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Extra-sensory perception, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Edwin J. Grace, 1955-1958 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Heart, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Job Applications, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Writing Course, 1936-1958 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Personal Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Scrapbook of news clippings (Box 2, Folder 5)
- News Print Scrapbook (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Liberal Party (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Press Releases (Box 2, Folder 2)
- News Clippings and Memos (Box 2, Folder 1)